the sodium potassium pump is an active
transport mechanism that is driven by
the breakdown of ATP and works through a
series of conformational changes in a
transmembrane protein 3 sodium ions bind
to the cytoplasmic side of the protein
causing the protein to change its
conformation in its new conformation the
molecule becomes phosphorylated at the
expense of a molecule of ATP the
phosphorylation induces a second
conformational change the translocates
the three sodium ions across the
membrane in this new conformation the
protein has a low affinity for sodium
ions and the three bound sodium ions
dissociate from the protein and diffuse
into the extracellular fluid the new
conformation has a high affinity for
potassium ions two of which bind to the
extracellular side of the protein the
bound phosphate now dissociates and the
protein reverts to its original
conformation exposing the two potassium
ions to the cytoplasm on the inside of
the cell this conformation has a low
affinity for potassium ions so the two
bound potassium ions dissociate from the
protein and diffuse into the interior of
the cell